（ヤサコ）
ヒゲたちのウワサによると
According to rumors amongst Bearded Ones,
紀元[きげん]:era|CE (Common Era)/AD (Anno Domini)
紀元5550分
when it's 5550 minutes,
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 約束[やくそく]:promise|convention|destiny, 地[ち]:earth|place|territory||, 地[つち, つし]:earth|the earth (historically, esp. as opposed to the heavens)|low-quality torinoko-gami (containing mud)|, 導く[みちびく]:to guide/to lead|to derive, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
ヤサコ様が約束の地に
お導きくださるそうです
Lady Yasako will take them to the promised land.
（ダイチ）だあ～！
あ～ もうダメだ！
Oh no!
I can't take it any more!
これで
フミエにまで―
Now I can't hold my head up high in front of Fumie, either!
頭[とう]:counter for large animals (e.g. head of cattle), 頭[あたま, かしら]:head|hair (on one's head)|mind||, 上がる[あがる]:to rise|to enter (esp. from outdoors)|to enter (a school)||, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
頭が上がらなく
なってしまった！
転落[てんらく]:fall/tumble|degradation, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
俺は もう転落人生だ
My life is on the verge of a total breakdown!
落ちぶれる[おちぶれる]:to be ruined (reduced to poverty)/to fall low/to go under
このまま
落ちぶれていくんだ
It'll only keep on going lower and lower!
末路[まつろ, ばつろ]:last days/the end/one's fate, 南極[なんきょく]:South Pole|the Antarctic/Antarctica, 凍死[とうし]:death from cold/freezing to death
そして末路は
南極で凍死するんだ～！
All I can do
is to await death by freezing at the South Pole!
南極[なんきょく]:South Pole|the Antarctic/Antarctica
（デンパ）なんで南極？
Why the South Pole?
一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace, 地球儀[ちきゅうぎ]:globe (map)
（ダイチ）
だって一番下だろ 地球儀の
It's the lowest place in the entire world, isn't it?
If I keep going lower, I'll eventually reach the South Pole, right?
落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 南極[なんきょく]:South Pole|the Antarctic/Antarctica
落ちてったら 最後には南極だろ！
（京子(きょうこ)）ウンチ！
Poop!
どわっ… 俺はウンチだ
I'm poop!
役に立つ[やくにたつ]:to be helpful/to be useful, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being
役に立たない存在なんだ～！
I'm completely useless!
やればできる:you can do it if you try
そんなことないよ
ダイチはやればできるよ
That's not true!
I'm sure you can succeed, Daichi!
ホント:truth/reality/actuality, 絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness
（ダイチ）ホントにそう思うか？
（デンパ）絶対そうだよ
Do you really think so?
I'm sure of it!
なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something, 気になる[きになる]:to be on one's mind|to feel like|to fancy
うん！
なんかそんな気になってきたぞ
Hey, I think I can now!
（足を踏む音）
（ダイチ）イッテ！
一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, トライ:try
（ダイチ）
というわけで もう一度
トライしてみようと思う
Anyway, I wanna try it once more.
Daichi's First Hair
イリーガル:illegal, 捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize
イリーガルを捕まえる
（デンパ）えっ？
I'll capture an Illegal.
イリーガル:illegal, いじめる:to tease/to torment/to persecute, やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（デンパ）
イリーガルをいじめるのは
もうやめようよ
Let's stop messing with the Illegals!
いじめる:to tease/to torment/to persecute, コンピューターウイルス:computer virus
（ダイチ）
なんだよ “いじめる”って
コンピューターウイルスだぞ
What do you mean, "messing with"?
It's a computer virus!
イリーガル:illegal, いじめる:to tease/to torment/to persecute, 手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to
イリーガルをいじめるなら
手伝わない
If you're going to mess with Illegals, I'm not going to help you!
メ… メタバグは どうすんだよ
But what about the metabugs?
拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
メタバグなら拾えばいいだろ！
僕 帰るよ
We can just scoop them up off the ground!
Good day!
イリーガル:illegal, いじめる:to tease/to torment/to persecute
分かった！
イリーガルはいじめない
All right!
I won't mess with Illegals.
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
だから帰らないでくれ…
So please, don't go.
らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
おっかしいな…
前はいたらしいんだけどな
How odd...
I'm sure they were here before.
しかし ちょっと分かってきたぞ
I think I've figured it out.
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
ヤツらはな 古い空間で
I think that those things
usually hang around in places where errors tend to occur, like an obsolete Space.
なおかつ:besides/furthermore|and yet, 誤差[ごさ]:measurement error/calculation error, やすい:cheap/inexpensive|calm, やすい:easy|likely to .../have a tendency to ..., 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 居る[いる]:to be (of animate objects)|to stay|verb indicating continuing action or state (i.e. to be ..ing, to have been ..ing), 居る[おる]:to be (animate)|verb indicating continuing action or state (i.e. to be ..ing)|indicates contempt or disdain for another's actions
なおかつ こういう誤差の
出やすい場所に居つくんだ
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, ほとんど:mostly/nearly/practically, 消す[けす]:to erase|to turn off power|to extinguish|
だが そういう場所は
ほとんどサッチーに消されている
Yet all those places are deleted by Satchii.
I see...
イリーガル:illegal
では ここに
イリーガルがいたのは なぜだ？
So why do you think that Illegals used to be here?
神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine
ここが神社だからだ
It's because it's a shrine!
なるほど:I see/That's right!/Indeed
（デンパ）あっ なるほど
Oh, I get it now!
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
どういうこと？
What do you mean?
神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
（ダイチ）
神社に サッチー入れないだろ？
Satchiis can't enter shrines, right?
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine
古い空間のある神社を
しらみ潰しにすりゃいいんだよ
We'll just have to search all the shrines thoroughly for obsolete Spaces.
（住職）こらー！
（３人）わあっ…
Hey!
とうとう:finally/at last/ultimately, とうとう:clashing of swords/felling of trees/ringing of an ax, 駅[えき]:station, 向こう[むこう]:opposite side|over there|the other party|
（デンパ）とうとう
駅向こうまで来ちゃったね
Oh geez, we ended up back at the station.
やっぱり:too/also|still, 絶滅[ぜつめつ]:destruction/extinction
（ダイチ）やっぱり
サッチーが絶滅させちゃったのかな
So Satchii really deleted them all...
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly
でも きっと
まだ どこかにいるよ
But I'm sure there must be some left somewhere.
明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
おう！　また明日も探そうぜ
Yeah, let's search for them again tomorrow.
妹[いもうと]:younger sister, 妹[いも]:darling (only of a woman)|one's sister|friend
…にしても ヤサコの妹
なんでついてくんだよ
Anyway, why the hell does Yasako's sister have to follow us?
離れる[はなれる]:to be separated|to leave|to leave (a job, etc.)|
うわっ 離れろよ！
Let go of—!
背負う[せおう, しょう]:to carry on one's back|to be burdened with|to have (something) in the background|
（ダイチ）なんで
こんなの背負ってんだ 俺は…
Why the hell am I carrying this kid?
Yes?
（ヤサコ）はーい
あら ダイチ君
Oh, it's you, Daichi.
これ
Here.
あら 京子
Ah, Kyoko...
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 誘拐[ゆうかい]:abduction/kidnapping/kidnaping
ヤダ… ダイチ君　まさか誘拐？
No way, Daichi!
Don't tell me you kidnapped her?
失敬[しっけい]:rudeness/saying good-bye/acting impolitely
し… 失敬な！
Y-You're so mean!
勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, 親切[しんせつ]:kindness/gentleness, 連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person)
勝手についてきたから
親切に連れてきてやったのに
And I brought her back even though she tagged along without our permission!
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
本当？　デンパ君
Is that true, Denpa?
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
（デンパ）うん ホントだよ
Yup, it's true.
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
デンパ君が言うなら本当よね
If you say so, it must be true.
じゃあね
Bye-bye.
からい:spicy/hot|salty, からい:salty (taste)/briny
せちがらいぜ
She's very unpleasant.
湯[ゆ]:hot water|hot bath|molten iron, 湯[タン]:soup
（ダイチの父）
あー いいお湯だった
Ah, that was such a good bath.
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
お前 次 入れ
You're next.
食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||, 汚い[きたない]:dirty|disordered|indecent (language, etc.)||, 見せる[みせる]:to show/to display
メシ食ってるときに
汚(きたね)えもん見せんな！
Can't you see I'm eating?
Don't show me that dirty stuff!
家庭[かてい]:home/family/household
（ダイチの父）
バカもん！　これが家庭ってもんだ
Idiot! This is what a family is.
全裸[ぜんら]:nude, 過ごす[すごす]:to pass (time)|to overdo (esp. of one's alcohol consumption)|to take care of||, 家庭[かてい]:home/family/household, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
全裸で過ごせない家庭なんて
家庭じゃない
A family where you can't walk around naked is not a real family!
家庭[かてい]:home/family/household, 全裸[ぜんら]:nude
家庭とは全裸　全裸とは家庭だ
Being family means being naked; being naked means being family!
ワーハハハハハ！
親父[おやじ, ろうや]:one's father/old man/one's boss
バカ親父(おやじ)が
Dad, you're so stupid.
So you say! But you were the one who was always running around butt-naked at home!
家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, フルチン:having the penis hang out (e.g. no trousers or pants), 走り回る[はしりまわる]:to run around
お前だって いつも家ん中
フルチンで走り回ってたじゃねえか
母ちゃん[かあちゃん]:mum/mom, ビール:beer
母ちゃん ビール ビール
Honey, beer, beer!
大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult
もう そんな年じゃねえの
俺は大人なんだよ
I'm not that kid any more!
I'm an adult now!
生える[はえる]:to grow/to spring up|to cut (teeth)
（ダイチの父）
ヘッ まだ生えてもいねえくせに
But you haven't even sprouted a single hair yet!
なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something
俺なんか お前の年には
ボッサボサだったぞ
At your age,
I was really hairy!
アッハハハハハ！
生える[はえる]:to grow/to spring up|to cut (teeth)
そのうち
ボッサボサに生えてくらあ！
You have to grow 'em like crazy!
はりきる:to be in high spirits/to be full of vigor (vigour)/to be enthusiastic
（ダイチ）
今日も はりきっていくぞ！
I'm in high spirits today!
Yeah!
（ダイチ）
なんで またいるんだ？　お前
Why the hell are you here again?!
（京子）いくぞ オー！
Let's go! Yeah!
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 不良[ふりょう]:bad/poor|delinquent
ただの空間不良か
It's just a standard glitch in the Space.
背負う[せおう, しょう]:to carry on one's back|to be burdened with|to have (something) in the background|
（ダイチ）なんで また
こんなの背負ってんだ 俺は…
Why the hell am I carrying her again?
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 空振り[からぶり]:striking (at something) and missing/in vain
（デンパ）結局 空振りだったね
We had no luck today, either.
（ダイチ）ああ そうだな
Yeah...
イリーガル:illegal
（デンパ）
ハァ… でもイリーガルって
I pity the Illegals; their habitats are diminishing.
住む[すむ]:to live (of humans)/to reside/to inhabit, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, どんどん:drumming (noise)|rapidly/steadily, 減る[へる]:to decrease (in size or number)/to diminish/to abate, かわいそう:poor/pitiable/pathetic
住む場所がどんどん減って
かわいそうだな
はーい
Yes?
あら ダイチ君
Oh, it's you, Daichi.
Here.
（ダイチ）これ
（ヤサコ）あら また
Again?
I told you, it's not what you think!
っつう:meaning/called/said, 勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, ついてくる:to follow/to come along with one/to accompany
だから違うっつうの
こいつが勝手についてくるの
She keeps tagging along without our permission!
ぶはっ…
D-Daichi!
近づく[ちかづく, ちかずく]:to approach/to draw near|to get acquainted with
ダ… ダイチ君
もう京子には近づかないでね
Don't you dare come near Kyoko ever again!
W-Wait!
被害者[ひがいしゃ]:victim/injured party/sufferer
ま… 待て！　こっちこそ被害者だ
I'm the victim here!
ファーストキス:first kiss
よくも俺のファーストキスを！
She stole my first kiss!
Y-Yasako, don't tell anyone about this!
ヤ… ヤサコ！
このこと誰にも言うなよ
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness
絶対だぞ！
Absolutely no one!
It's not growing yet...
生える[はえる]:to grow/to spring up|to cut (teeth)
（ダイチ）まだ生えねえな
Or maybe they grow here first?
先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.)
それとも こっちが先かな？
着信[ちゃくしん]:arrival (e.g. post, signal)|receiving/incoming
（電話の着信音）
（ダイチ）あっ なんだ 着信か
What... Oh, a call.
Hello, Denpa?
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
おう デンパか
明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future
えっ 明日 来られない？
Eh? You can't come tomorrow?
Okay, then the day after.
あさって:day after tomorrow
うん じゃあ あさってな
Eh? Yasako's sister?
妹[いもうと]:younger sister, 妹[いも]:darling (only of a woman)|one's sister|friend
えっ ヤサコの妹？
Well, I'll try to—
適当[てきとう]:suitable/proper|noncommittal, あしらう:to treat/to handle|to arrange
あれは適当にあしらって…
もしもし:hello (e.g. on phone)|excuse me! (when calling out to someone)
（デンパ）
もしもし ダイチ？
Hello? Daichi?
What's wrong, Daichi?
どうしたの？　ダイチ
Bri...
ボ… ボッサボサ…
Bristly...
What's that?
何？　何がボッサボサなの？
What's bristly?
Daichi?
もしもし:hello (e.g. on phone)|excuse me! (when calling out to someone)
ダイチ？　もしもし？
Hello?
The Next Day
Kyoko!
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
（ヤサコ）京子 何してるの？
ほら 帰るわよ
What are you doing?
Let's go home.
Poop!
ウンチ！
しかたない:it can't be helped/it's inevitable/it's no use
もう… しかたないわね
What am I going to do with you?
The Day After
Yes. I see.
電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device)
（デンパ）うん そうなんだ
電話にも出ないんだ ダイチ
Daichi isn't even answering the phone.
I wonder if he's planning some kind of prank?
やらかす:to fail/to blunder|to drink up, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
（フミエ）また なんか
やらかす気じゃないでしょうね？
Who knows...
（デンパ）さあ？
回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||, 電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device)
あっ １回だけ電話あったよ
As a matter of fact, he called me once.
What did he say?
（フミエ）なんて？
Well, he asked me
憔悴[しょうすい]:emaciation/haggardness|exhaustion, 声[こえ]:voice
憔悴(しょうすい)した声で
with a really exhausted voice, "Have you grown any yet?"
生える[はえる]:to grow/to spring up|to cut (teeth)
“お前は まだ
生えてないのか？”って
Oh?
どのみち:anyway/anyhow/at any rate, 明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future
（フミエ）はあ？
まあ どのみち 明日 分かるでしょ
Anyway, we'll probably find out tomorrow.
Why?
なんで？
Because tomorrow's a school day.
明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, 登校[とうこう]:attendance (at school)/going to school, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
（フミエ）
明日 登校日よ　忘れたの？
Don't tell me you forgot?
The Day After That
Hey, hey!
遅刻[ちこく]:lateness/late coming
（ウチクネ）
おらおら 遅刻すんぞー！
You're gonna be late!
What's this?
裏切り[うらぎり]:treachery/betrayal/perfidy
（ナメッチ）なんだよ
何しに来たんだよ 裏切り者
What are you doing here, traitor?
Where's Daichi?
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25)
（デンパ）ダイチは？
（ナメッチ）あんな人 知らねえ
I don't know a thing about that guy.
I wonder where Daichi's gone off to...?
（デンパ）ダイチ
どこ行っちゃったんだろうな…
Oh, Daichi!
あっ ダイチ！
ど… どうしたの？
そんなにゲッソリして
What happened? What's with that long face?
BE—
ヒ… ヒゲ～！
BEARD!
You look kinda...
色[いろ]:colour|complexion|appearance||, 色[しょく]:counter for colours, 艶[つや]:gloss|charm|color, 艶[えん]:charming/fascinating/voluptuous
（フミエ）
この色といい 艶といい…
An Illegal?
イリーガル:illegal
（ヤサコ）イリーガル？
South Pole...
南極[なんきょく]:South Pole|the Antarctic/Antarctica
南極だ
Where did he get this?
拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather
（フミエ）
どこから拾ってきたの？　これ
I have no idea.
（デンパ）
それがよく分からないんだ
Anyway, let's get to the bottom of this.
ともかく:anyhow/anyway/somehow or other, 実物[じつぶつ]:real thing/original/actual, 実物[みもの]:ornamental plant used primarily for the visual effect of its fruit, 調べる[しらべる]:to examine/to investigate/to check up
（フミエ）
ともかく 実物を調べましょうよ
おうおう:sometimes/often, おうおう:discontented/unhappy, 子供[こども]:child/children
（メガばあ）おうおう
まだ子供だと思ってたら―
And I thought that he was still a child!
坊主[ぼうず]:Buddhist priest|close-cropped hair|boy|
この坊主も
もう こんな年かい
But my, he's already come of age.
Cut it out!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, イリーガル:illegal
やめてよ
イリーガルだって言ってるでしょ
I told you, it's because of an Illegal.
（メガばあ）うむっ
An ultra high-powered, super-magnifying cybermicroscope!
超[ちょう, チョー]:super-/ultra-|over (after a number or counter), 高性能[こうせいのう]:high efficiency/high performance, スーパー:super, 拡大[かくだい]:magnification/enlargement/expansion, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 顕微鏡[けんびきょう]:microscope, マシン:machine
超高性能
スーパー拡大電脳顕微鏡マシン！
Take a look!
おりゃ！
Times two...
倍[ばい]:twice/double|times, 更に[さらに]:furthermore/again/after all, 拡大[かくだい]:magnification/enlargement/expansion
２倍じゃ これを更に拡大する
If we zoom in more...
若い[わかい]:young|immature|low (number), 肌[はだ, はだえ]:skin|body (in the context of intimate bodily contact)|surface|
ヒヒヒッ 若い肌はええのう
Young hair is so lovely!
K-Knock it off...
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
（ダイチ）や…やめてくれよ
（メガばあ）動くでない
Don't move.
Epidermis - Dermis
皮膚[ひふ, ひフ]:skin, 表面[ひょうめん]:surface|outside|appearances, 先端[せんたん]:pointed end/tip/fine point, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
（メガばあ）
うむ… 皮膚の表面から先端までが
古い空間じゃな
It's all an obsolete Space: from the surface of the skin to the tips of the hairs.
So that beard is an Illegal?
やっぱり:too/also|still, イリーガル:illegal
（ハラケン）やっぱり
このヒゲはイリーガルか
This boy is changing what's around him into an obsolete Space.
周り[まわり]:circumference/girth|surroundings, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 置き換える[おきかえる]:to replace/to move/to change the position of
（フミエ）こいつも自分の周りを
古い空間に置き換えているのね
So maybe,
いずれ:where/which|anyway, 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face, 霧[きり]:fog/mist|spray, 覆う[おおう]:to cover/to hide/to conceal
じゃあ いずれ 顔が霧に覆われて…
one day, he'll be covered in fog...
S-Scary.
恐ろしい[おそろしい]:terrible/dreadful|surprising
お… 恐ろしい
Let's try to see the borders this time.
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, 先っちょ[さきっちょ]:end/tip/point
今度は 先っちょを見てみようか
It's  moving!
動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
（フミエ）なんか動いてるわ
Let's zoom in some more.
拡大[かくだい]:magnification/enlargement/expansion
（メガばあ）拡大してみよう
Eyes!
（ヤサコ）目だわ！
They're living...
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, イリーガル:illegal
（フミエ）
生きてる… 生きたイリーガルだ！
They're living Illegals!
They're talking.
会話[かいわ]:conversation
（ハラケン）会話している
Sis.
お姉ちゃん[おねえちゃん]:familiar form of "older sister"|form of address for young adult female
（京子）お姉ちゃん
Kyoko, not now.
あとにする:to leave behind|to put off/to postpone, 大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||
京子 あとにして
今 大変なことに…
We have a big prob—
A BEARD!
ヒゲ～！
（一同のおびえる声）
（京子）エヘッ
W-Why does Kyoko have a beard?!
（ヤサコ）
な… なんで京子にヒゲが？
伝染[でんせん]:contagion/infection
（フミエ）
伝染… 伝染するのよ このヒゲは
Contagious...
The beard is contagious!
K-Kyoko!
近づく[ちかづく, ちかずく]:to approach/to draw near|to get acquainted with
きょ… 京子ちゃん 近づかないで！
Don't come any closer!
チュー:kiss, チュー:nine, 大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||
そ… そうよ
チューしたら大変なことに…
T-That's right!
If you kiss someone, it'll be big trouble—
大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||
大変なこと？
Big trouble?
エヘッ
チュ～！
Kiss—!
ぶはっ…
イヒヒッ
We have to stop her!
得る[うる]:to be able to .../can ...|to get, 得る[える]:to get|to understand|to receive something undesirable (e.g. a punishment)|
やむを得ないわ
I invoke the right of a preemptive self-defensive strike!
集団的[しゅうだんてき]:collective/group, 自衛権[じえいけん]:right of self defense/right of self defence, 発動[はつどう]:putting into operation|invocation
集団的自衛権 発動よ！
（ビームの発射音）
（京子）ウンチ～！
POOP!
Auto-restore in process
治る[なおる]:to be cured/to get well|to get mended, お年玉[おとしだま]:New Year's gift (usu. money given to a child by relatives and visitors), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 軽い[かるい, かろい]:light (i.e. not heavy)|light (i.e. of foot)|non-serious||
（ヤサコ）これで治るんなら
お年玉２年分なんて軽いものだわ
If this fixes it,
two years' otoshidama would be a cheap price to pay.
（メガばあ）だといいがな
I hope that's all it takes.
どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
どういう意味？
What do you mean?
Complete
なんで？
Why?
自動[じどう]:automatic/self-motion|intransitive verb, 復元[ふくげん]:restoration (to original state)/reconstruction, 一部[いちぶ]:one part/one portion|one copy (e.g. of a document), 個人情報[こじんじょうほう]:personal information, 修復[しゅうふく, しゅふく]:restoration/repair/mending
自動復元は
一部の個人情報も修復するのじゃ
The autorestore also restores the partition that holds personal information.
領域[りょういき]:area/domain/territory, 入り込む[はいりこむ, いりこむ]:to go into/to come into|to become complicated
このヒゲは その領域に
入り込んでおるのじゃろう
Maybe the beard is part of that domain.
お年玉[おとしだま]:New Year's gift (usu. money given to a child by relatives and visitors), 損する[そんする]:to lose (money, etc.)|to have wasted one's (time, etc.)/to have one's efforts come to naught
お年玉２年分 損した
We lost two years' otoshidama...
生える[はえる]:to grow/to spring up|to cut (teeth)
（フミエ）生えてきたわね
The hair has started to grow on him, too.
But it's only been an hour!
経つ[たつ]:to pass (of time)/to elapse
（ハラケン）
まだ１時間しか経ってないのに
感染力[かんせんりょく]:infectious capacity, 増す[ます]:to increase/to grow
感染力が増してるわ
The epidemic's strength has increased!
不思議[ふしぎ]:wonder/miracle/strange
（メガばあ）
う～ん… しかし不思議じゃ
Hmm, how mysterious.
It appears that the beard only grows near the mouth, just like a real one.
本物[ほんもの]:genuine article/real thing/real deal, 同じく[おなじく]:similarly/same (idea)/same (name), 口[くち]:mouth|opening|mouth (of a bottle)||, 口[く, こう]:mouth/speech|counter for people or implements, 周り[まわり]:circumference/girth|surroundings, 生える[はえる]:to grow/to spring up|to cut (teeth)
本物のヒゲと同じく
口の周りしか生えんようじゃ
So, no kiss, no infection.
うつる:to move (house)/to transfer (department)|to change the target of interest or concern, うつる:to be reflected/to harmonize with (harmonise)/to come out (photo)
じゃあ キスでもしなきゃ
うつらないのね
食い止める[くいとめる]:to check/to hold back/to stop
よかった
３人までで食い止められて
Great! I'm so glad we didn't get infected.
指[ゆび, および]:finger/toe/digit, 指[さし, サシ]:between (e.g. two people)|hindrance|arrhythmic section of recitative in noh music||
（フミエ）ゆ… 指に
O-On her finger...
生える[はえる]:to grow/to spring up|to cut (teeth)
（ヤサコ）ヒゲが生えてる
...there's hair growing!
Look, look!
生える[はえる]:to grow/to spring up|to cut (teeth)
（京子）ねえ 見て見て
デンスケにも生えてるよ
Even Densuke is growing some!
You have no defenses at all!
食い止める[くいとめる]:to check/to hold back/to stop, じゃん:isn't it
食い止めてないじゃん
A few hours later
嫁に行く[よめにいく, よめにゆく]:to marry (of a woman)/to become a bride/to marry into (a family)
もう お嫁に行けないわ！
I can't become a bride any more!
諦める[あきらめる]:to give up/to abandon (hope, plans)/to resign oneself (to)
諦めちゃダメよ ヤサコ！
Don't give up, Yasako!
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly
そうだよ ヤサコ
きっと なんとかなる！
Don't worry, Yasako!
We'll beat this somehow.
ノンキ:carefree/optimistic/careless, 言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say
あんたは男だから
そんなノンキなこと言えんのよ！
You can speak so casually about this because you're a man!
B-But I'm...
（ハラケン）でも 僕は…
I touched Kyoko's mouth with my finger.
口[くち]:mouth|opening|mouth (of a bottle)||, 口[く, こう]:mouth/speech|counter for people or implements, 指[ゆび, および]:finger/toe/digit, 指[さし, サシ]:between (e.g. two people)|hindrance|arrhythmic section of recitative in noh music||, 触る[さわる]:to touch/to feel
（ヤサコ）京子の口を指で触ったわ
（フミエ）とにかく このまま―
Anyway, at this rate,
we can't do anything but wait for Megabaa's vaccine.
ワクチン:vaccine
メガばあのワクチンを
待つしかないわね
いらっしゃる:to come/to go|is (doing), 麦茶[むぎちゃ]:barley tea, 飲む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||
（静江(しずえ)）いらっしゃーい
麦茶あるから飲んでね
Hello, everyone!
There's some barley tea, so help yourselves.
Good.
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse), うつる:to move (house)/to transfer (department)|to change the target of interest or concern, うつる:to be reflected/to harmonize with (harmonise)/to come out (photo)
よかった… メガネかけない人には
うつらないのね
We can't infect people who don't wear glasses.
It's ready!
（メガばあ）でけたぞ！
Is the vaccine ready?
ワクチン:vaccine, どこどこ:such-and-such a place
（ヤサコ）ワクチンできたの？
（フミエ）どこどこ？
Where, where?
It's not the vaccine that's ready.
ワクチン:vaccine
うむ ワクチンはできなんだが…
But something interesting came out.
面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
（メガばあ）面白いものができた
言語[げんご, ごんご]:language, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
言語を持っておるから
もしやと思ったが…
Since they have a language, I thought that perhaps they could also...
住居[すまい, じゅうきょ]:dwelling/house/residence
（ハラケン）これは？
（メガばあ）住居じゃ
Are these...?
Houses!
Wh-What?
（一同）な… なんだって？
All right, young'uns. Watch this.
さよう:action/operation/effect, さよう:like that|that's right/indeed
（メガばあ）さよう これも見よ
They've started to develop a means of transportation.
交通手段[こうつうしゅだん]:means of transportation/transportation system/way of getting around, 発達[はったつ]:development/growth, 始める[はじめる]:to start|to open (e.g. a store)|to start ...
交通手段が発達し始めておる
都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 文明[ぶんめい]:civilization/civilisation|Bummei era (1469.4.28-1487.7.20)
（ハラケン）都市文明？
A city?
Not only that.
（メガばあ）
それだけではない ほれ
This.
A moxibustion?
灸[きゅう, やいと]:moxibustion, まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 効く[きく]:to be effective|to do its work|to be possible to use
お灸(きゅう)？
まさか お灸が効くとでも…
Do you seriously think that moxibustion is gonna work?
I was able to tap into their conversations!
こやつ:he/she|this, 声[こえ]:voice, 聞き取る[ききとる]:to catch (a person's words)/to make out|to find out by asking, 成功[せいこう]:success/hit
こやつらの声を
聞き取ることに成功した
Wh-What?!
（一同）な… なんだって？
What's more, it's compatible with an old translation server...
しかも:moreover/furthermore|nevertheless, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 翻訳[ほんやく]:translation|de-encryption|rendering, サーバー:server, 言語[げんご, ごんご]:language, 近い[ちかい]:near|close (in time)|close (relationship)||
（メガばあ）
しかも古い翻訳サーバーの
言語に近いものでな
so I created a translation device!
翻訳[ほんやく]:translation|de-encryption|rendering, 機[はた]:loom, 機[き]:chance|machine|aircraft||, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
翻訳機ができてしもうた
Stop creating useless things!
余計[よけい]:too many|unnecessary|abundantly, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
（一同）よ… 余計なもん
作ってんじゃねえ～！
Anyway, if we come into contact with anyone, we shouldn't infect them.
触れる[ふれる]:to touch|to experience|to touch on a subject||, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration, 広まる[ひろまる]:to spread/to be propagated
（ヤサコ）
とにかく誰にも触れさせなければ
広まらないわよ
Yeah.
うん じゃあ
Bye.
It's crazy.
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech, しゃべれる:to talk/to chat/to chatter
…にしても
まさか言葉がしゃべれるとはね
They even have their own language.
What's this?
所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel
何？　何？
“こんな所に止めるな”？
"No parking there!"
That must be a traffic cop...
交通[こうつう]:traffic/transportation/communication, 渋滞[じゅうたい]:congestion (e.g. traffic)/delay/stagnation
これは交通渋滞ね
"Don't cry just because you tripped on the floor."
転ぶ[ころぶ, まろぶ]:to fall down/to fall over, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 泣く[なく]:to cry/to weep/to sob
“転んだくらいで泣いちゃダメよ”
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 親子[おやこ, しんし]:parent and child
フフッ これはきっと親子ね
It must be a parent-child conversation.
The most common one is "I'm hungry".
一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace
〝ハラヘッタ 〞が
一番多いのね
The second one is "my back hurts".
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 腰[こし, コシ]:back/lower back|body (of hair, noodle, paper, etc.), 腰[ごし]:posture/position/pose, 痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding
次は〝腰が痛い 〞？
腰[こし, コシ]:back/lower back|body (of hair, noodle, paper, etc.), 腰[ごし]:posture/position/pose, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
フフフッ
腰なんてあるのかしら？
Do they even have backs?
Chat?
発言[はつげん]:statement/remark/observation
“発言”？
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
ま… まさか
Don't tell me—
Hello
It worked!
通ずる[つうずる]:to be open (to traffic)|to flow (liquid, current)|to be understood||
通じたわ
They talk just to talk.
ほとんど:mostly/nearly/practically, 愚痴[ぐち]:idle complaint/grumble|moha (ignorance, folly), ばっかり:only/merely|approximately, まるで:quite/entirely|as if, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
（ヤサコ）ほとんど愚痴ばっかり
まるで人間みたい
Just like humans.
How cute.
可愛い[かわいい, かわゆい]:cute|dear|cute little
可愛いわ
Oh no!
大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||
あら 大変！
At this rate, they'll crash!
ぶつかる:to strike against/to collide with|to encounter, 止まる[とまる]:to stop (moving)|to stop (doing, working, being supplied)|to alight, 止まる[とどまる]:to remain/to abide|to be limited to
このままじゃ
ぶつかるわ… 止まって！
Stop!
What was that voice? - We were going to crash! - Thank God!
I'm so glad!
よかった
What?
大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||
大変！　死にたいですって？
He wanted to die?
"Knock it off."
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 希望[きぼう]:hope/wish/aspiration
“やめて！
きっと まだ希望はあるわ”
"There's always hope."
Oh no!
大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||, 火山[かざん]:volcano, 噴火[ふんか]:eruption
大変！　火山が噴火するわ
A volcano is going to erupt!
"Everyone, run away."
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
“みんな逃げて”
Good!
うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious
よかった うまくいったわ
It went well.
大勢[おおぜい, たいぜい]:crowd of people/great number of people|in great numbers, 大勢[たいせい]:general trend/current thought, 助かる[たすかる]:to be saved|to escape harm|to be helped
何？　何？
“これで 大勢 助かりました”
What?
"A lot of us were saved thanks to you."
命[いのち]:life|lifetime|most important thing||, 命[めい]:command|life|destiny, 恩人[おんじん]:benefactor/patron
“あなたは命の恩人です”
"You just saved our lives."
教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
“お名前を教えてください”
"Please, tell us your name."
よーし:alright/all right/right on
よーし
Well then.
“私の名はヤサコ”と…
"My name is Yasako."
とうとう:finally/at last/ultimately, とうとう:clashing of swords/felling of trees/ringing of an ax, 徹夜[てつや]:all night/all-night vigil/sleepless night
（ヤサコ）で とうとう徹夜よ
So in the end, I was awake all night long.
神殿[しんでん]:temple/sacred place/shrine, あちこち:here and there/all around|to get things in the wrong order (back to front), 建てる[たてる]:to build/to construct
神殿が あちこちに建てられたわ
And they've built altars everywhere!
ワクチン:vaccine
えっ ワクチン？
Eh? The vaccine?
…って なんだっけ？
What's that?
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
まだみたい
It doesn't look like it's ready yet.
この世[このよ]:this world/the present life (in contrast to the land of the dead), 終わり[おわり]:the end, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
（フミエ）そう
こっちは この世の終わりみたいよ
Really?
Over here, it looks like the end of the world.
It's infected people all over town!
街中[まちなか]:downtown, 街中[まちじゅう]:the whole town/all over the town/throughout the town, 感染[かんせん]:infection/contagion
街中に感染してるわ
（ヤサコ）えっ なんで？
Eh, why?!
こっちが聞きたいわよ
That's what I want to know!
大忙し[おおいそがし]:very busy (person or thing)
サッチーも大忙しだわ
Satchii is on the prowl.
おかげさま:(somebody's) backing/assistance/thanks to (somebody)
（オバちゃん）おかげさまでね
（フミエ）ひぃ…
It's all thanks to you.
（オバちゃん）また お前らか
（フミエ）うわ～！
You again...
うっ！　ぐはっ…
我慢[がまん]:patience/endurance/perseverance, 告訴[こくそ]:accusation/complaint/charge
もう我慢できない
お前ら告訴する！
I can't take it any more!
I'm filing a complaint against you!
ワクチン:vaccine, ソフト:soft, 開発中[かいはつちゅう]:under development
ま… 待って！
今 ワクチンソフトを開発中よ
Wait! We're creating a vaccine!
Really?
本当か？
（フミエ）ほ… 本当よ！
R-Really!
持ってこい[もってこい]:just right/ideal|fetch!, もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally
できたら すぐに持ってこい！
もちろんタダでだ
Bring it to me immediately once it's completed!
For free, of course!
ポチ 待て！
Pochi, stop!
外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman), 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face, 壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.)
（フミエ）外にいたら 間違いなく
サッチーに顔を壊されるわ
If we go outside, Satchii will shoot us in the face!
治る[なおる]:to be cured/to get well|to get mended
でも それで治るわけだな
But if we did that, we would heal.
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 手段[しゅだん]:means/way/measure
最後の手段としてはありえる
We may as well consider it a last resort for recovery.
面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
（ヤサコ）
アハッ 面白すぎるわ これ
This is fun!
ホント:truth/reality/actuality, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
ホントに神様にでもなったみたい
I feel like I've become their god!
サボる:to be truant/to play hooky/to skip school, 働く[はたらく]:to work|to function|to commit (e.g. a crime)|, なさる:to do
ほら そこ
サボってないで働きなさい
Hey you!
Stop slacking, and get back to work!
ターン:turn, 完成[かんせい]:complete/completion|perfection
あと３ターンで完成するんだから
It'll be complete in three turns.
面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
面白そうだな
That looks fun.
軍事[ぐんじ]:military affairs, 衝突[しょうとつ]:collision/crash|conflict
（ダイチ）ああっ！
何 軍事衝突してるんだよ
What's that fight?
せっかく:stone burial chamber, せっかく:with trouble/at great pains|rare, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, 壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.)
せっかく作ったダム壊すなよ
Don't destroy the fields I've just created!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|, 約束[やくそく]:promise|convention|destiny
もう 早く返してよ
ちょっとだけって約束でしょ
Give it back to me, quickly!
You promised you'd only be a little while!
順番[じゅんばん]:turn (in line)/order of things/sequential order, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise)
その前に私でしょ？
もう 順番 守ってよ
But it's my turn next, right?
Respect our turn order!
ハマる:to fit|to be fit for (a job, etc.)|to fall into||
みんな ハマっちゃったな
Everybody's being drawn to it...
離す[はなす]:to separate/to part/to divide
（フミエ）
ああ… もう目が離せないわ
I can't take my eyes off it!
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 飛行機[ひこうき]:aeroplane/airplane/aircraft, 飛ぶ[とぶ]:to fly/to soar|to jump
聞いて！
最近 飛行機 飛んだのよ
You know, they were able to make a plane fly!
文明[ぶんめい]:civilization/civilisation|Bummei era (1469.4.28-1487.7.20), だいぶ:lengthy (of a book, etc.)/voluminous|most (e.g. most part), だいぶ:considerably/greatly/a lot, 発達[はったつ]:development/growth, してき:historic/historical, してき:pointing out/identification
（ハラケン）みんな
文明がだいぶ発達してきたようだね
It appears that everyone has made great progress.
I'm already making plans for outer space!
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 計画[けいかく]:plan/project/schedule
私は もう宇宙計画よ
通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 成功[せいこう]:success/hit, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
京子のヒゲと
通信に成功したらしくて
It appears that they've managed to communicate with Kyoko's hairs,
空前[くうぜん]:unprecedented/record-breaking, ブーム:boom/rage/fad
今 空前のＳＦブームなの
so now it's a SF boom!
ケンカ:quarrel/brawl/fight, 壊れる[こわれる]:to be broken/to break|to fall through
（ダイチ）ああっ ケンカすんなよ
ダムが壊れる！
Enough! Stop fighting!
The dam will collapse!
戦争[せんそう]:war
戦争って本当にムダなんだね
War is so futile.
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, プライド:pride, 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
最後はプライドしか残らないし…
In the end, the only thing you have left is your pride.
I always tell them, "don't fight", but...
争う[あらそう]:to compete|to quarrel|(usu. in negative form) to deny (e.g. evidence), 争う[あらがう]:to go against/to fight against/to oppose, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.)
争うなって
ずっと私も言ってるんだけど…
一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace, 進む[すすむ]:to advance|to precede|to make progress||, 進む[すさむ]:to grow wild/to run to waste
一番進んでるのは
ヤサコのヒゲだね
The most advanced hair is Yasako's.
今 どうなってる？
What are they up to now?
ロケット:rocket
あとちょっとで
ロケットができるかも
A little longer and they'll probably make a rocket!
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
（フミエ）ホントに？
Really?
戦争[せんそう]:war, 初[はつ, うい]:first/new, 初[うぶ]:innocent/naive|birth-, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行[ひこう]:aviation/flight|to fly, 飛行[ひぎょう]:flying without hindrance
戦争さえしなけりゃ
もうすぐ初の宇宙飛行が…
If only they didn't fight,
they'd soon launch their first spaceship—
初[はつ, うい]:first/new, 初[うぶ]:innocent/naive|birth-, 大気[たいき]:atmosphere, 圏外[けんがい]:(being) out of range (e.g. mobile network, radar, missiles)/(being) out of contention/(being) beyond influence, 脱出[だっしゅつ]:escape/break-out|prolapse
（ハラケン）やったー！
（フミエ）初の大気圏外脱出だわ
They did it!
It's their first flight outside the atmosphere!
歴史的[れきしてき]:historic/historical/traditional, 瞬間[しゅんかん]:moment/second/instant
（ハラケン）歴史的瞬間だ
What a historic moment!
おめでとう:congratulations!/an auspicious occasion!, おめでとう:Japanese sweets made with glutinous rice and azuki bean paste
（デンパ）ヤサコ おめでとう…
Congratulations, Yasako!
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
ま… まさか
D-Don't tell me it's...
核[かく]:pit (of a fruit)|core|nucleus|, 核[さね]:pit (of a fruit)|core|tongue (piece of wood used to connect two boards)|, 戦争[せんそう]:war
か… 核戦争？
A nuclear war?!
文書[ぶんしょ, もんじょ]:document/writing|document addressed to someone in particular (jargon used in paleography), 黙示録[もくしろく]:Revelation (book of the Bible)/the Apocalypse, 章[しょう]:chapter/section|medal
（ヒゲ）
「オコノギ文書」 黙示録 835章
"From the Book of Okonogi.
Revelation #835.
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
ヤサコ様は言われた
So saith Lady Yasako:
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 破滅[はめつ]:ruin/destruction/fall
“このままでは
必ずや世界の破滅”
'And thus, 'tis the end of the world.
起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen
“ハルヒゲドンが起こる”と…
An armageddon will occur.'
So, that frightening prophecy was about this.
恐ろしい[おそろしい]:terrible/dreadful|surprising, 予言[よげん]:prediction/prophecy/prognostication, 予言[かねごと]:promise/prediction
（ヒゲ）恐ろしい予言とは
このことだったのだ
我々[われわれ]:we
我々は どこから来て
どこに行くのだろう…
'Where did we come from?
What are we heading towards?'"
Don't give up, people!
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
み… みんな頑張って
なくなる:to die, なくなる:to be lost (e.g. luggage)/to be missing|to be used up
私 もうメガビーなくなるわ！
I'll run out of mega-be!
僕も
Me too!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face, 破壊[はかい]:destruction/disruption|(application) crash, 自滅[じめつ]:ruining oneself/destroying oneself/self-destruction
もう やめて！
顔を破壊したら自滅なのよ
Stop it, now!
If you damage my face, I'll self-destruct!
Even though you're their goddess,
ヤサコは神なのに
言うことを聞かないのか？
why won't they listen to you?
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now
そ… それが最近はダメなの
Well, it's been total chaos recently.
哲学者[てつがくしゃ]:philosopher
どこかの哲学者が
“ヤサコは死んだ”とか言い出して
Some philosopher said:
"Yasako is dead."
Oh!
返事[へんじ]:reply/answer/response
（ハラケン）あっ 返事が来た
A reply!
争い[あらそい]:dispute/strife/quarrel, やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, 敵[かたき]:rival|revenge|spouse, 敵[てき]:opponent/rival|menace, 滅ぼす[ほろぼす]:to destroy/to overthrow/to wreck
（ヤサコ）“争いをやめたら
敵に滅ぼされるだけだ”って
"If we were to stop the war,
we'd be destroyed by the enemy."
"But to wage war is stupid."
ケンカ:quarrel/brawl/fight, 愚か[おろか]:foolish/stupid
“でもケンカするのは
愚かなことよ”
Another reply!
返事[へんじ]:reply/answer/response
返事だ
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, ケンカ:quarrel/brawl/fight
“では ヤサコ様たちは
ケンカをしないのですか？”
"So, Lady Yasako, do you and your friends never fight?"
"Just because you're friends,
同士[どうし, どし]:fellow/mutual/companion, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 仲良く[なかよく]:on good terms with/on cordial terms with|to make friends with
（ヤサコ）“仲間同士だからって
必ず仲良くできるんですか？”
does that mean you're always at peace?"
ほっと:feeling relieved/(sigh of) relief
このまま ほっときましょうよ
Let's just let them fight like this.
フミエちゃん
Fumie!
It's better if they kill themselves off!
文明[ぶんめい]:civilization/civilisation|Bummei era (1469.4.28-1487.7.20), ケンカ:quarrel/brawl/fight, 自滅[じめつ]:ruining oneself/destroying oneself/self-destruction
こんな文明
ケンカして自滅したほうがいいのよ
B-But how can you...
（ヤサコ）そ… そんな
ヒドいわ フミエちゃん
You're so mean, Fumie!
Oh? The missiles stopped.
ミサイル:missile, 止まる[とまる]:to stop (moving)|to stop (doing, working, being supplied)|to alight, 止まる[とどまる]:to remain/to abide|to be limited to
あれ？　ミサイルが止まってる
Oh, it's true!
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
あっ ホントだ
Maybe I convinced them!
説得[せっとく]:persuasion, 通ずる[つうずる]:to be open (to traffic)|to flow (liquid, current)|to be understood||
説得が通じたのかも
（ミサイルの発射音）
（ハラケン）あっ ダメか…
No...
You see? Look!
なさる:to do, ほっと:feeling relieved/(sigh of) relief
ほら見なさい！
もう ほっときましょう
Let's abandon them to their fate.
An interplanetary war!
星間[せいかん]:interstellar, 戦争[せんそう]:war
（一同）星間戦争？
S-Stop it!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（ヤサコ）や… やめて～！
The civil war on her face has stopped, but...
顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face, 同士[どうし, どし]:fellow/mutual/companion, 戦い[たたかい]:battle/fight/struggle, 収まる[おさまる]:to be in one's place|to be delivered|to be settled||
自分の顔同士の戦いは
収まったけど…
War is such nonsense.
戦争[せんそう]:war, むなしい:empty/void|vain
戦争は むなしいわ
Where...
間違う[まちがう]:to make a mistake/to be incorrect/to be mistaken, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
どこで…
どこで間違ってしまったの？
Where did I go wrong?
My poor hairs!
可愛い[かわいい, かわゆい]:cute|dear|cute little
私の可愛いヒゲたち…
Oh? What's this?
（ヤサコ）あら？
（フミエ）どうしたの？
They're trying to talk to me.
語りかける[かたりかける]:to make a speech/to address
（ヤサコ）私に語りかけてきたわ
"After paying with a large number of victims,
とりかえす:to regain/to recover/to get back, 犠牲[ぎせい]:victim/sacrifice/scapegoat, はらう:to pay (e.g. money, bill)|to brush off/to wipe away, はらう:to exorcise/to cleanse/to purify
“とりかえしのつかない
犠牲をはらって”
we've finally understood the futility of war."
同士[どうし, どし]:fellow/mutual/companion, 戦い[たたかい]:battle/fight/struggle, むなしい:empty/void|vain
“仲間同士の戦いの
むなしさに…”
Great! They've finally understood!
気づく[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise
やったー！　気づいてくれたわ
What else?
（フミエ）それで？
"All the various planets have communicated
全[ぜん]:all/whole|pan-, 惑星[わくせい]:planet, コンタクト:contact, 果たす[はたす]:to accomplish/to achieve|to do ... completely
（ヤサコ）
“全惑星とコンタクトを果たし”
and pieced the situation together."
我が[わが]:my/our/one's own, 種族[しゅぞく]:race/tribe/family, 現状[げんじょう]:present condition/existing state/status quo, 把握[はあく]:grasp/catch/understanding
“我が種族の現状を把握した”
"Because of the numerous wars,
幾多[いくた]:many/numerous, 戦争[せんそう]:war, 我々[われわれ]:we, 文明[ぶんめい]:civilization/civilisation|Bummei era (1469.4.28-1487.7.20), 旧[きゅう]:ex-/former/old, 旧[ふる]:used item/secondhand item|old, 世紀[せいき]:century/era, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
“幾多の戦争で我々の文明は
旧世紀に戻ってしまった”
our civilization has returned to that of a bygone era."
"We beg you, Lady Yasako,
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 我々[われわれ]:we, 行く末[ぎょうまつ, ゆくすえ]:fate/one's future|end of (text) line, 決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||
“どうかヤサコ様のお力で
我々の行く末を決めてほしい”
to somehow show us, with your power, our fate."
So in the end, it's just a prayer to God.
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 神頼み[かみだのみ]:entreaty to a deity, 勝手[かって]:one's own convenience|surroundings|convenience||
最後は神頼みか 勝手なもんだ
Only when it's convenient, huh.
Yeah, just like us humans.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
そう 人間と同じようにね
But there isn't a spot on the head where Satchii won't attack...
顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face, 襲う[おそう]:to attack|to succeed (someone in a post, role, etc.)|to make a sudden visit, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
でも顔の上で
サッチーにも襲われない場所なんて
ハッ！　あるわ １つだけ
There is one.
Only one!
A new haven for us!
新天地[しんてんち]:new land/new world/new sphere of activity
（ヒゲ）新天地だ！
Thank you, Lady Yasako!
様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
（ヒゲ）ヤサコ様 ありがとう！
"The time is 5760 minutes.
紀元[きげん]:era|CE (Common Era)/AD (Anno Domini), 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state, 導き[みちびき]:guidance
（ヒゲ）紀元5760分
ヤサコ様のお導きにより―
Thanks to the advice of Lady Yasako,
the race of the bearded ones has arrived safely, and has colonized the promised land."
族[ぞく]:tribe|(taxonomical) tribe|group (of the periodic table), 族[やから]:party (of people)/set (of people)/clan, 無事[ぶじ]:safety/peace/quietness, 約束[やくそく]:promise|convention|destiny, 地[ち]:earth|place|territory||, 地[つち, つし]:earth|the earth (historically, esp. as opposed to the heavens)|low-quality torinoko-gami (containing mud)|, 移住[いじゅう]:migration/immigration, 果たす[はたす]:to accomplish/to achieve|to do ... completely
ヒゲ族は 無事
約束の地に移住を果たした
Mr. Tome
旦那[だんな]:master (of a house, shop, etc.)|husband (informal)|sir||
（ヤサコ）トメさんの旦那さんは
always hides that area when he goes out.
外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 部分[ぶぶん]:portion/section/part, 隠す[かくす]:to hide/to conceal
外に出るとき
必ずあの部分を隠すわ
So, Satchii won't be able to find it, right?
見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
じゃあ サッチーには
見つからないってわけね
I'd like them to live in peace there.
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals, ひっそり:quiet (place)/still|inconspicuously, 生き延びる[いきのびる]:to survive/to live long
あそこで
ひっそりと生き延びてほしいね
A few days later
But, a few days later,
数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount, 後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|
（ヤサコ）
でも それから数日後のことです
we went to see the situation of the bearded ones after some time.
久しぶり[ひさしぶり]:a long time (since the last time)/it's been a while (since I last saw, mailed, etc., you), 様子[ようす]:state|appearance|sign, 私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us
久しぶりに ヒゲたちの様子を
見に行った私たちは―
We found a message written there.
置き手紙[おきてがみ]:letter left behind by someone who has departed/farewell letter, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
置き手紙を見つけました
We found these words in the message:
手紙[てがみ]:letter, 記す[しるす, きす]:to write down/to note|to remember
手紙には こう記されていました
"Nor was this the place for us to live.
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 住む[すむ]:to live (of humans)/to reside/to inhabit, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
“ここも私たちの住むべき場所では
ありませんでした”
We just wanted to get to the adults' civilization quickly,
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult, 文明[ぶんめい]:civilization/civilisation|Bummei era (1469.4.28-1487.7.20)
“私たちは
早く大人の文明になりたかった”
but we really were too young for that.
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 幼い[おさない, いとけない]:very young|childish/immature, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
“でも それには
私たちは幼すぎたのです”
We decided to leave on a journey to find our promised land.
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 約束[やくそく]:promise|convention|destiny, 土地[とち, どおじ]:plot of land/lot|locality, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), 旅[たび]:travel/trip/journey, 旅[りょ]:500-man battalion (Zhou-dynasty Chinese army), ことにする:to make a distinction/to differ/to be different, ことにする:to decide to|to pretend that
“私たちは本当の約束の土地を
探す旅に出ることにしました”
We thought that the promised land
約束[やくそく]:promise|convention|destiny, 土地[とち, どおじ]:plot of land/lot|locality, もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance
“その約束の土地は
もしかしたら―”
might as well be the one we were born in.
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 生まれ[うまれ]:birth/birthplace|born in (country, month, imperial era, zodiac year, etc.), 故郷[ふるさと, こきょう]:home town/birthplace|ruins
“私たちの生まれ故郷ではないかと
思うのです”
We wonder whether there's no war at all in that place.
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 争い[あらそい]:dispute/strife/quarrel, 平和[へいわ]:peace/harmony, 平和[ピンフ, ピンホー]:concealed winning hand consisting of chows, a pair that isn't a value pair, and an open wait, 土地[とち, どおじ]:plot of land/lot|locality
“そこは きっと争いのない
平和な土地なのではないか”
Or at least, so we hope."
気がする[きがする]:to have a certain mood or feeling/to have a hunch
“そんな気がしてならないのです”
Preview
Next time on Dennou Coil:
次回[じかい]:next time (occasion), 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil
（ヤサコ）
次回 「電脳コイル」
The Last Plesiosaur.
The Last Plesiosaur
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 首長[しゅちょう]:head (of organization, organisation)/chief, 竜[りゅう, たつ]:dragon (esp. a Chinese dragon)|naga|promoted rook
〝最後の首長竜 〞
See you next time!
楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation
お楽しみに